Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף Daf is כ"א, chaf-alef, and
we pick up at the bottom of כ' עמוד ב', chaf amud-bet,
and we are where it says
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. It's about half of the way down, about
fifteen lines before the lines get wide. תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: כל
האמור בפרשת כהנים שכהן מיטמא להם, אבל מתאבל עליהם. Kol ha'amur b'parshas
kohanim shekohein mitama lahem, avel mitabel aleihem. Anybody said in the פרשה
parsha of the כהנים kohanim that a כהן, kohein, a male כהן
kohein is not allowed to become טמא למת, tamei le'meis, but nevertheless
it says that he becomes טמא tamei to his immediate relatives,
so those are the ones that the aspect of becoming טמא tamei
speaks towards a responsibility to take care of them in their death
and therefore becomes the model of those that there is an obligation
for אבילות aveilus regarding those people. ואלו הן, Ve'elu hein, and these
are they: אשתו, isho, wife—interesting that it's mentioned first because it's the
one that's really not explicit in the verse, as I mentioned yesterday,
debate between the רמב"ם Rambam and the ראב"ד Ra'avad whether the idea
that a כהן kohein can violate his, you know, the prohibition for
one's wife is biblical or rabbinic, according to a startling statement in
the רמב"ם Rambam even though you're violating a negative prohibition, it's only
the Rabbis who included the category of wife.
אביו, אמו, אחיו, ואחותו, Aviv, imo, achiv, ve'achoto, father, mother, brother, sister;
בנו ובתו, b'no u'vito, daughter and son. Those are the seven. הוסיפו
עליהם, Hosifu aleihem, now they added on these basic seven: אחיו ואחותו
הבתולה מאמו. achiv ve'achoto habetulah me'imo. First of all, all of this
sense of siblings, you know, certainly when you're dealing with a patriarchal
system, is defined through a relationship with the father. So the Rabbis
added to them half-brother and sister, thank you, via by the mother,
that that was included. Notice, by the way, אחותו הבתולה, achoto habetulah,
virgin, because in the text that's what refers to in terms of
the כהן kohein because once she is married to another man, she
no longer is like the family of the כהונה, kehunah, she's connected
to her husband's family. So therefore, so they added the relationship by
the mother. ואחותו נשואה בין מאביו ובין מאמו, Ve'achoto nesuah bein me'aviv
u'vein me'imo, and a married sister. Okay, so even though again, once
a woman is married in this,
you know, classic sort of traditional patriarchal system, she's related to the
family of her husband and sort of has left her father's house
and is no longer related to that family. Interestingly, the Rabbis continue
to recognize her as part of that family and still have an
obligation of אבילות aveilus even after she is married.
Where are we?
Question?
Yes.
So if the sister marries and then gets divorced? Yeah. She becomes
תרומה terumah again, but does the כהן kohein
become—Yeah, I'm not going to deal with that now. Okay. כשם שמתאבל
עליהם, כך מתאבל על שניים שלהם. K'shem shemitabel aleihem, kach mitabel al
shniyim shelahem. And the same way one is מתאבל mitabel for these
immediate family, one is מתאבל mitabel for the next generation, which would
mean like a wife's father or mother, or a wife's child that
is not a person's own, or a husband's father, mother, husband's child
that is not a person's own. That would be the next generation.
דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, אינו מתאבל אלא על בן בנו
ועל אבי אביו. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, eino mitabel ela al
ben b'no ve'al avi aviv. No, the only case would be a
grandson or a grandfather. Those, you know, you have a direct relationship
to as opposed to, let's say, another example would be a niece
or a nephew, that would be a brother's child. So things that
are next generation that you're not really directly related to, you would
not have אבילות aveilus according to חכמים, Chachamim, according to שמעון בן
אלעזר, Shimon ben Elazar, only grandfather and grandson. Now we know that
that's not, we don't do any of that. We don't do any
of the next generation. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, and the Sages say:
כל שמתאבל
עליו מתאבל עמו. Kol shemitabel alav mitabel imo. Anybody who you would
be an אבל avel for if they were to die, you observe
אבילות aveilus with that person. So if the person would be an
אבל avel if their sister were to die, then if their sister
is sitting שבעה shiva for a child, a niece or a nephew,
then that person would sit שבעה shiva with his or her sister.
Okay, so that is, it sounds like it's saying any of the
other generations because if you know because then that's exactly it. If
you identify with the person who, you know, if that's the person
who is sitting שבעה shiva and you're sitting,
if the person sitting שבעה shiva is the person you would sit
שבעה shiva for, then you're basically sitting שבעה shiva for the next
generation, either one generation up or one generation down. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara says: היינו תנא קמא. Hainu tana
kama. That's exactly the תנא קמא tana kama which says that you
sit שבעה shiva not only for these immediate relatives but also for
the next generation or the previous generation. So the גמרא Gemara says:
איכא בינייהו עמו בבית. Ika beina'ihu imo babayit.
No, there's a fundamental difference. According to the תנא קמא, tana kama,
somebody would directly sit שבעה shiva for a grandfather, for a grandson,
for— a father-in-law, mother-in-law for a niece, for a nephew; that would
be considered your relative and therefore sit שבעה. shiva. According to this,
the framing it that you sit שבעה shiva together with a person
for whom you would yourself sit שבעה shiva for, like so if
a person's sister or brother is sitting שבעה shiva then she or
he would sit שבעה shiva together with them, then it's framing it
not because of the relationship to the one who has died but
because of the relationship to the one sitting שבעה. shiva. And therefore
it's really only a out of respect for the one sitting שבעה.
shiva. And that's why the גמרא Gemara says איכא בינייהו עמו בבית.
ika beinaihu imo babayis. The difference is is that person around in
the house? So if a person's, for example, sister or brother is
sitting שבעה, shiva, then out of respect to the sister or brother
one would observe the שבעה shiva with him or her, but that's
not because of a direct שבעה shiva for the niece or the
nephew or father-in-law or mother-in-law. Okay, so כי הא, ki ha, like
the story דאמר ליה רב לחייא בריה, de'amar lei Rav L'Chiya brei,
Rav said to Chiya's son, וכן אמר ליה רב הונא לרבה בריה,
vechen amar lei Rav Huna leRabba brei, Rav Huna said to Rabba's
son, באפיה be'appa in her face, presumably your wife's face, if your
wife is sitting שבעה, shiva, נהוג גביה לותא nehog gabei lusa in
her presence observe אבילות, aveilus, ודלאו אפיה delo appa not in her
presence לא תינוג גביה לותא lo tignog gabei lusa do not observe
אבילות. aveilus.
Presumably this would be for mother-in-law or a father-in-law. Okay, מר עוקבא
שכיב ליה בר חמוה. Mar Ukva shachiv lei bar chamuha.
So Mar Ukva, the his
mother-in-law's son died, so basically his like his
brother-in-law died. סבר למיתב עליה שבעה ושלשים. savar lemisav alei shiva ushloshim.
So
he thought to observe a normal שבעה shiva for this person. If
you go by this idea of second generation as it
were, so if he would sit שבעה shiva for his wife, he's
going to sit שבעה shiva for his
brother-in-law. על רב הונא לגביה, a'al Rav Huna legabeih, so Rav Huna
went to visit him, אשכחיה ashkachei he found him, אמר ליה סעודתא
בעית למיכל, amar lei se'udaisa ba'is lemichal,
so he said to him, "Do you want
to eat a like a סעודתא se'udaisa means like a mourner's meal?"
Meaning are you considering yourself a mourner? לא אמרו לכבוד אשתו אלא
חמיו וחמותו. lo amru lichvod ishto ela chamiv vechamoso.
Even when they said, and this is that a person observes, a
man here would observe together with his wife to show respect to
his wife who's sitting שבעה, shiva, that's only for a parent, that's
only for
father-in-law or mother-in-law, not here where it's a brother-in-law. דתניא detanya
we've learned in a
ברייתא, Braitisa, מי שמת חמיו וחמותו, mi shemeis chamiv vechamoso, if a
man's mother-in-law or father-in-law died, אינו רשאי לכוף אשתו להיות כוחלת
ופוקסת. eino rashai lachofos ishto lihyos kocheles u-fokeses. So the הוה אמינא
Havamina is his wife is sitting שבעה, shiva, he can't say that
he doesn't want his wife to look disheveled for him, so what
she's sitting שבעה shiva I want her to look nice. No, he's
not allowed to force his wife to put on makeup, אלא כופה
מטתו ונוהג עמה אבילות. ela kofeh mittaso venoheg immah aveilus. And not
only that, כופה מטתו ונוהג עמה אבילות. kofeh mittaso venoheg immah aveilus.
He has to turn over his bed and to practice אבילות aveilus
together with her. וכן היא שמת חמיה או חמותה, vechain hi shemeis
chamiha o chamosah, and now here finally from the woman's perspective, if
her father-in-law or mother-in-law died, אינה רשאי להיות כוחלת ופוקסת. eino rashai
lihyos kocheles u-fokeses. So now she's not the one sitting שבעה, shiva,
right, her husband is sitting שבעה, shiva, so she however cannot put
on makeup out of respect to her husband's שבעה, shiva, אלא כופה
מטתה ונוהגת עמו אבילות. ela kofeh mittasah venoheges immo aveilus.
But she turns over her bed and practices אבילות aveilus together with
him. So there you see the idea of a spouse practicing אבילות
aveilus together with the other spouse who's really sitting שבעה. shiva. ותניא
אידך vetanya idach which shown in another ברייתא, Braitisa, אף על פי
שאמרו אינו רשאי לכוף אשתו להיות כוחלת ופוקסת, af al pi she'amru
eino rashai lachofos ishto lihyos kocheles u-fokeses, although they said that a
man cannot force his wife to put on makeup, presumably she's sitting
שבעה, shiva, באמת אמרו מוזגת לו את הכוס ומצעת לו את המטה
ומרחצת פניו ידיו ורגליו, be-emes amru mozeges lo es hakos umatzah lo
es hamitah u-meracheset panav yadav veraglav,
she can still has to do those wifely duties of pouring the
mixing the drinks and spreading the bed and washing his face. So
questions ended up overturned?
Well, okay, so that's going to be the issue.
קשיא אהדדי, kashya ahaddi, we have a contradiction exactly that because of
רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, what's the contradiction? Okay, so she doesn't put
on makeup but she takes care of these duties. The contradiction is
as רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom said, דהכא תני מצעא לו מטתו והכא
תני כופה מטתו. de-hacha tnai matza lo mittaso ve-hacha tnai kofeh mittaso.
So
what are you doing? Is he observing אבילות aveilus together with her
or not? Is this bed overturned or not? אלא לאו שמע מינה
כאן בחמיו וחמותו כאן בשאר קרובים. ela lav shema mina kan be-chamiv
ve-chamoso kan bishear kerovim. It's a difference whether it's his mother-in-law or
father-in-law or whether it's another relative through his wife like a brother-in-law
or sister-in-law. שמע מינה, shema mina, you hear that. So what we've
done now is
we've laid out three opinions about more indirect relatives. The first opinion
is that really it seems like it doesn't matter if it's next
generation, that's all related and it's all שבעה, shiva, much broader definition
of who one sits שבעה shiva for. Then came רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar who said no it is broader but
it's only
grand... But there is a concept of observing שבעה shiva together with
one's spouse out of respect for one's spouse, or together with a
person who one would sit שבעה shiva for, then if that person
is him or herself sitting שבעה, shiva, an observance of שבעה shiva
together with that person out of respect. And however, though there are
two limits. Number one, it's only in that person's presence. And number
two is, is that as we're at least seeing by the case
of the wife or the husband, by the spouse, it's only for
a mother or father, not for another relative. Okay, and this also
comes up, you know, if a person's parent is sitting שבעה shiva
for a grandparent. So a person doesn't have a direct responsibility to
sit שבעה shiva for the grandparent, but some aspects of observing within
this person's presence. Now to what degree do we really do that
is relatively minor nowadays. I mean, you know, obviously there's like being
when you're directly in the presence, you're not going to go ahead
and like I don't know, start the you know watching the ballgame
together with when the person, I mean that's not even against sitting
שבעה, shiva, but you know you're going to act in a respectful
way in the שבעה shiva house. But you know even this last
aspect we don't, you know, in practice we do relatively, in a
relatively limited way. Let's keep looking. So גמרא Gemara says like this:
What, right, even shave, right, you know.
Yeah exactly, so it's only in the presence. But if you take
a look at
תוספות, Tosafos, באפיה נהג אבילות, be-afei nahag aveilus, תוספות Tosafos clarifying like
what's the extent of this. He says פירש בתוספות בכל דיני אבילות
נעילת הסנדל ורחיצה וסיכה וכולן כל זמן שהוא בפניה. peirush be-Tosafos bekhol
dinei aveilus ne'ilas ha-sandal ve-rhitza ve-sicha ve-khulan kol zman she-hu be-faneha. Okay
as long as you're in the immediate presence of a spouse let's
say, you would not have you you take off your shoes. Right,
we don't do that. פרק קמא דכתובות Perek Kama de-Kesuvos קאמר ka-amar
עמו בבית imo ba-bayis ושרמי מפי לאפי ve-sharei mi-afa le-afa שמה בכל
הבית. shema bekhol ha-bayis. He doesn't know does it mean literally directly
in the presence or maybe anywhere in the same house. Okay but
anyway but according to this, you know, if a person's spouse is
sitting שבעה shiva he or she would not wear shoes, would not
go and wash their face, at least if they were in the
same room.
What if it's not a spouse, it's your brother and he's sitting
שבעה shiva for his wife, meaning your sister-in-law and you're in your
brother's house, do we have to do any of this?
So right, so also that's a good question. According to the חכמים
Chachamim it doesn't spell out exactly right beyond the spouse, it doesn't
so to speak spell that out, although the phrase of the חכמים
Chachamim was anybody a person would sit שבעה shiva for, so it
could possibly extend in those directions as well. So it's not fully
spelled out. Okay. Yeah. So גמרא Gemara says like
this, שמע מינה. Shema Mina. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hakhi, תנו
ולא אמרו לכבוד אשתו אלא חמיו וחמותו בלבד. tanu ve-lo amru likhvod
ishto ela khami ve-khamoso bilvad. Now again notice by this phrase בלבד
bilvad to חמיו וחמותו, khami ve-khamoso, it phrases it as לכבוד אשתו.
likhvod ishto. So it's also framing it much much more limited, you
don't have the broader sense you got by the חכמים Chachamim of
anyone a person would sit שבעה shiva for, any relatives sitting שבעה.
shiva. You know, it's framing it much more in terms of the
spouse. אמימר Ameimar שכיב ליה בר בריה. shakhav lei bar brei. Now
אמימר's Ameimar grandson died. קרע עילויה, kara iluyei, he did קריעה kriya
which you know so what was that based on, the idea of
was he really obligated, is it going back to the earlier discussion
the opinion that a person would sit שבעה shiva for a grandfather,
grandmother, or grandson, granddaughter? Not clear, but he did קריעה kriya on
his grandson. אתא
בריה קרע באפיה. ata brei kara be-apay. So his son came and
he did קריעה kriya in his presence. Now who did קריעה kriya
in whose presence? So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom said that אמימר Ameimar
did קריעה kriya a second time, it's not clear why. So the
better reading or the reading I prefer is in תוספות, Tosafos, which
is the son did קריעה kriya in his father's presence. Okay because
now the son is doing קריעה kriya for his son, he's doing
the קריעה kriya that he's really obligated to. The father, he hasn't
done it yet, the father of the dead boy is now doing
קריעה kriya in the grandfather's presence.
So אדכר דמיושב קרע. itkar de-meyushav kara. So אמימר Ameimar realized the
first time he did קריעה kriya he did it when he was
sitting, because now he's seeing his son do קריעה kriya and it's
reminding him and he sees the son standing up like Oh my
God I did קריעה kriya the wrong way. It's like you know
you walk into שול shul and they're doing מוסף Musaf and you
realize Oh my God it's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh I forgot to.
Okay anyway, so קם קרע מעומד, kam kara me-umad, he got up
and he did קריעה kriya standing. So this is now we're going
to move from the idea of doing אבילות aveilus for a indirect
relative, which was how it started, it was his grandson, and move
to discussion of doing קריעה kriya standing. אמרי ליה רב אשי לאמימר,
amrei lei Rav Ashi le-Ameimar, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to
אמימר, Ameimar, קריעה דמעומד מנלן? kriya de-me-umad minalan? So אמימר Ameimar you
were so מקפיד makpid to stand up and do קריעה kriya second
time, where do you know you have to do קריעה kriya standing?
דכתיב, dekhtiv, because the verse says, ויקם איוב ויקרע את מעילו. Vayakam
Iyov vayikra et me'ilo. איוב Iyov rose up and he rent his
garment. So אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's the basis, so ועמד
ואמר לא חפצתי לקחתה, ve-amad ve-amar lo chafatzti le-kachtah,
by the case of the ייבום yibbum we have that the man
gets up and says when he refuses חליצה, chalitza, I do not
desire to take her. הכא נמי, hakha nami, would you also say
you have to do that standing? And because it says ועמד, ve'amad,
okay, and actually that's more prescriptive than a narrative and descriptive, so
then it sounds like you have to stand. והתניא, vehatanya, but we
taught in a ברייתא, braitah, בין יושב בין עומד בין מוטה, bein
yoshev bein omed bein mutah,
whether a person is sitting or standing or leaning, you can do
חליצה. chalitzah. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he says back to
him, or you can do this proclamation. התם כתיב ועמד ואמר, hatam
ktiv ve'amad ve'amar,
he shall stand and he shall say. It says and he stood
and he said, so it's not as prescriptive as you, as you,
you know, as you would as you wanted it to be. Okay,
so הכא כתיב ויקם ויקרע. hacha ktiv vayakom vayikra.
Here it says and he rose up and he tore. So somehow
the, although it is still different, one is a narrative and descriptive
and the other is prescriptive. But nevertheless, saying in the sense of
shall stand as opposed to and he stood, indicates that it's not
strictly required. Now that's one way of reading it. The other difference
is ועמד ואמר, ve'amad ve'amar, although this doesn't sound like it's what
the גמרא gemara is saying as opposed to
ויקם. vayakom. ועמד ואמר ve'amad ve'amar can just mean and he shall
like, you know, get up and go, like, and he shall rouse
himself and say. ועמד ואמר ve'amad ve'amar doesn't literally have to mean
stand, okay? So that's another possible point that the גמרא gemara is
making, like, and he, you know, and he shall then sort of
get up and say, doesn't literally mean get up.
Exactly. But anyway, here it seems to be more whether it's in
the, you know, whether it's in the shall or not. אמר רמי
בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, מנא לן לקריעה שעומד? mena lan
likriah she'omed? Okay, so we're looking for another source. Because even though
we have now sort of defended that source, we're still not totally
happy. שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says, ויקם איוב ויקרע. vayakom Iyov vayikra.
So again, but we're going back to the verse by איוב. Iyov.
He rose up and he rent his garments. So הגמרא hagemara says
that, דילמא מילתא יתירתא הוא דעבד. dilma milta yetirata hu de'avad. One
minute, maybe that's he's just acting in an excessive manner, that's not
strictly required. ואי לא תימא הכי, ve'i lo teima hachi, if you
don't say that, ויגז את ראשו, vayagez et rosho, when it says
that he shaved his head, הכא נמי, hacha nami, does it mean
you have to shave your head if a person is sitting שבעה?
shivah? אלא
מהכא, ela mehacha, fine, from the following verse. ויקם המלך ויקרע את
בגדיו. vayakom hamelech vayikra et begadav. The king arose, King David, and
he rent his garments.
So ודילמא מילתא יתירתא עבד. vedilma milta yetirata avad. Maybe there too,
he's being a little bit excessive. ואי
לא תימא הכי, ve'i lo teima hachi, if you don't say that,
now first of all תוספות tosafot points out that this was before
his son died. So if you take a look, I'll just I'll
just pause for a moment and look at תוספות. tosafot. וישתחו ארצה
אף על גב דשכיב כתיב נמי גבי הילד דבת שבע אף על
גב דלא גבי מיתה, vayishtachu artzah af al gav deshachiv ktiv nami
gabi hayeled deBat Sheva af al gav delo gabi mitah, the child
hadn't died yet, right? He was praying that the child survive, he
hadn't died. אלא על בנו דשמא הואיל והנביא אמר לו מות ימות
הרי הוא כמת. ela al bno deshema ho'il vehanavi amar lo mot
yamut harei hu kemet. So interesting, although technically he was not yet
doing the practices of אבלות, avelut, he was sort of anticipating the
impending tragedy and maybe we can infer from that. So that's fascinating
in itself. Okay, but the גמרא gemara anyway did not untap that.
So back to the גמרא. gemara. Says maybe the fact that what
David did was itself excessive. ואי לא תימא הכי, ve'i lo teima
hachi, if you don't say that, וישתחו ארצה, vayishtachu artzah, it says
he laid on the ground. הכא נמי, hacha nami, so would you
also say a person has to lay on the ground? והתניא, vehatanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, braitah, ישב על גבי מיטה על גבי
כסא, yashav al gabei mitah al gabei kisei, a person sits on
a bed or on a chair, על גבי אודייני, al gabei udayni,
which is some type of, how do they translate אודייני udayni there?
Some type of a seat. I think it's like a big, like
a basket or something. Or, anyway, mortar? What, a mortar? Oh, oh
yeah, like I guess a big mortar. Right, right, right. Okay, yeah,
that's what רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, מכתשת. machteshas. Mortar, yeah, whatever,
like a big, you know, you turn some big thing upside down,
like a big box upside down, I mean, a mortar, whatever. Okay,
or,
גדולה, gdolah, now the better גרסא girsa here is גדולה מכולן אמרו,
gdolah mikulan amru, more than all this they said that אף אפילו
על גבי קרקע לא יצא ידי חובתו. af afilu al gabei karka
lo yatza yedei chovato. Not only if you sit on a seat,
oh, that's too honorable to sit on a seat, you're not יוצא,
yotze, but actually they say that even if you do it on
a more lowly way, sit directly on the ground, you're not יוצא.
yotze. Why? ואמר רבי יוחנן שלא קיים כפיית המיטה. ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan
shelo kiyam kfiyat hamitah. A person did not fulfill the upturning of
the bed. So there's an idea of both physically turning the bed
upside down and sitting on the upside down bed, like sitting on
a lowly chair. Presumably, like sitting on the ground, sometimes people would
sit on the ground סתם, stam, you know, people sit on the
ground. Sometimes we hear about the rabbis giving, you know, their classes,
everybody is sitting on the ground. So that the real demonstration of
אבלות avelut is neither the ground nor the nice chair, but like
on this like lowly thing or this upturned bed, we're back to
the upturned bed. So anyway, so you see what King David did
was not הלכות אבלות, hilchot avelut, because sitting on the ground is
not הלכות אבלות, hilchot avelut, so you can't bring any evidence from
that. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, כעין ארצה.
ke'ein artzah. No, he was doing the laws of אבלות. avelut. When
it says he sat on the ground, it meant like being on
the ground, so he was on a low bed, on an upturned
bed, it was close to the ground. And still arguing that what
King David did was practices of אבלות, avelut, and since he rose
up to rent his garment, you see that you have to stand.
to do the rending of the garments standing up. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara has these two proofs. You know, it has problems with
them, but nevertheless, these are the proofs that the גמרא Gemara presents.
Okay.
So maybe you didn't do it standing up, you gotta go back
again and do it?
Yeah. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. I mean, what happened if somebody can't
stand? That's a good question. Okay. אלו דברים שאבל אסור בהן. Elu
devarim she'avel assur bahen. Finally, we're going to get to an actual,
like, distilled list of the practices of אבילות, aveilus, although even this
list, as we will see, is not complete.
The following things an אבל ovel is not allowed to do: אסור
במלאכה assur bimelacha cannot do work. The right? We talked about that
before, we're going to talk about it again. וברחיצה ubirechitzah bathing, this
is all during שבעה. shiva. ובסיכה ubissichah anointing, ובתשמיש המטה uvitashmish hamitah
sex, ובנעילת הסנדל ubine'ilas hassandal shoes.
Right?
What does this all sound like, by the way? יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, right? And they're אסור לקרות בתורה בנביאים ובכתובים ולשנות במשנה במדרש
בהלכות ובאגדות. assur likros baTorah biNevi'im uvaKesuvim ulishnos baMishnah bamidrash bahalachos uv'aggados.
Person can't learn תורה, Torah,
which now it's sounding more like תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. Guess why?
Because תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is מנהגי אבילות. minhagei aveilus. Okay, so
therefore these other things that are expressions of joy, so are the
first ones, you know, issues about like also, right? This is issues
we rose, we raised about how much are practices of אבילות aveilus
more like, you know, expressions of
pain and of suffering and so on or, you know, are they
something else? The issues that apply for שלושים, shloshim, right, about haircut
and the clothes, right? And those are similar as we noted to
מצורע metzora and so on, those might be one person is not
in the immediate aftermath of the death. It's not during שבעה, shiva,
it's not as much of an expression of this like of the
pain, but it still is maybe more of this sort of sense
of like a little bit not fully back and integrated into society
aspect. These are during the immediate שבעה, shiva, you know, again, the
fact that they parallel also issues of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you
know, basic sense of just like enjoying oneself, certain aspects of pleasure
or expressions, you know, that would be inappropriate, and certainly joy in
terms of the תורה, Torah, that seems to at least be the
focus of this list, yes.
Every שבעה shiva house I've ever been to, they learn משניות Mishnayos
so there's a נשמה... neshama...
yeah, so there's ways of dealing with that of saying, yeah, it's
not really תלמוד תורה talmud torah or something like this but there
are definitely ways of dealing with that. Okay.
So, yes, the sense
of joy you mentioned about יום כיפור... Yom Kippur...
what? Oh, that יום כיפור Yom Kippur was a day of joy.
Right. Yeah, so that's an interesting dual nature of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, that is true. Okay. So now, now it's also worth mentioning
is, well, you know, let's finish this part and then I'll go
back and say something. So we're going to elaborate on the דף
daf on the תלמוד תורה talmud torah part. אם רבים צריכין לו,
im rabbim tzrichin lo, but if a person is needed for the
community, particularly as we're going to see in the תלמוד תורה-ic talmud
torah department, אינו נמנע, eino nimna, a person does not hold himself
back. ומעשה שמת בנו של רבי יוסי בציפורי, uma'aseh shemeis beno shel
Rebbi Yose b'Tzippori, רבי יוסי's Rebbi Yose son died,
ונכנס בית המדרש ודרש כל היום כולו, venichnas beis hamedrash vedarash kol
hayom kulo, and he showed up to the בית המדרש beis hamedrash
and he spent the whole day expounding, giving a תורה Torah lecture.
רבה בר בר חנה אתרע ביה מילתא, Rabbah bar bar Chana itra
bei milsa, now רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana an
event occurred to him, meaning like, you know, it's sort of like
the euphemism where you would say suffered a loss, but it's even
more abstract, a thing happened to him. By the way, I do
have to say that in הלכות אבילות, Hilchos Aveilus, probably, I mean
I can't, I haven't done a rigorous analysis of it, but I
would probably more than anywhere else in ש"ס Shas you have, you
know, examples. You have case, you know, you have real-life examples of
almost every single discussion. Here's the הלכה, halacha, here's a case. Here's
the הלכה, halacha, here's a case. Because everybody deals with אבילות, aveilus,
right? It's the one sort of הלכה halacha that everybody is going
to deal with in their life. We all deal with גלות... golus...
Yeah, I know, but still, it's like, you know, it's
whatever it is, both in the גמרא, Gemara, in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
you know, there's so many cases where תוספות Tosafos says, or when
רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam sister died, or when this happened to רבינו
תם, Rabbeinu Tam, and when this happened or whatever, so there's like
you really sense the
universal reality of death and of dealing with and of the practices
of אבילות. aveilus.
So, רבה בר בר חנה אתרע ביה מילתא, Rabbah bar bar Chana
itra bei milsa, רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana suffered
a loss, סבר דלא למיפק לפירקא, sevar delo lemipak lepika, he thought
not to go out to the, you know,
to the, to the פירקא, pirka, to the teaching of the lecture.
אמר ליה רבי חנינא, amar lei Rebbi Chanina, so רבי חנינא Rebbi
Chanina said to him, אם היו רבים צריכין לו אינו נמנע. im
hayu rabbim tzrichin lo eino nimna. No, we talked that if the
masses need him, you shouldn't hold yourself back. So again, what's never
really fully explained here is, let's say the person doesn't want to
go, like just forget the הלכה, halacha, it doesn't feel appropriate. Anyway,
so, you know, is there a gray space here where you're allowed
to but you're not obligated to, you know? So anyway, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't explore that. סבר לאוקמי אמורא עליה, sevar le'ukmei amora alei,
he said fine, if I gotta go, then I'll have my אמורא
amora stand with me. The אמורא amora was what I would call
the loudspeaker. He was the guy that you would say over the
lecture to, and then he would be the one with the really
loud and deep and resonant voice that would sort of announce, you
know, sort of repeat everything you said to him, would repeat it
to the whole, you know, to everybody so everybody could hear. So
he figured that was what he was going to do, if he's
going to give a שיעור shiur he needs his אמורא. amora. אמר
ליה רב, amar lei Rav, so רב Rav said to him, תניא,
tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, brayisa, ובלבד שלא יעמיד תורגמן. uvillvad
shelo ya'amid turgaman. You cannot have a תורגמן turgaman or similarly an
אמורא. amora. because that is too much of a sign of respect
and of taking a status position. All right, so what are you
supposed to do? So on the one hand, it's too much status,
I mean you need to teach תורה, Torah, but that's too much
status to be embracing during this period. So ובהיכי עביד, v'heichi avid,
what would you do? כי הא דתניא, ki ha detanya, like we
learned in a ברייתא. braisa. מעשה ומת בנו של רבי יהודה בר
אלעאי, ma'aseh umet beno shel Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai, the son of
Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai died, which is Rabbi Yehuda, ונכנס לבית המדרש,
venichnas l'veit hamidrash, he went to the בית המדרש beit hamidrash to
give a שיעור shiur during שבעה. shiva. ונכנס רבי חנניה בן עקביא,
venichnas Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya, now Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya came with
him, וישב בצדו, vayeshev betzido, and he sat next to him. Now
Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya is another rabbi, he's not just a translator,
he was a colleague. So he sat next to him. ולחש הוא
לרבי חנניה בן עקביא, velachash hu l'Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya, so he
said to Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya what he was going to say,
line by line presumably, ורבי חנניה בן עקביא לתורגמן, veRabbi Chananya ben
Akavya latorgeman, and Rabbi Chananya ben Akavya was the one who said
to the announcer, והתורגמן השמיע לרבים, vehatorgeman hishmia larabim, and the announcer
announced it.
So it's like you're getting your colleague to, you know...
Yeah, but then it more appears like the one who is talking,
is sort of taking that normal position of status is the one
who's directly speaking to the translator. From an observer's point of view,
if a second person speaks to the translator and the translator announces,
it looks like it's coming from the second person, not from the
first person as much. That seems to be, I mean it's not
just a trick I think it was, or you know technically I
did it, I think the status is less when it's more removed.
Okay.
Now what's interesting here is a couple of things. First of all,
תוספות Tosafot points out that what's not mentioned in this is the
exceptions that are mentioned in תשעה באב Tisha B'Av about the sad
parts of תנ"ך Tanakh and so on, and the sad sort of
topics of learning. So if you take a look at the תוספות
Tosafot ואסור, v'assur, he says בשם רבנו זקני כתב שרבנו יעקב, beshem
Rabbeinu Zikni katav sheRabbeinu Yaakov, which is presumably רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam,
היה עושה בימי אבלו באיוב ובקינות ובדברים הרעים שבירמיה, haya oseh bimei
evlo b'Iyov u'v'Kinot u'vidvarim hara'im she'b'Yirmya, the things that are allowed during
תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. He says they are not allowed here, משום
דלא תני להו בשמעתין כמו בתשעה באב, mishum d'lo tani lehu b'shmatin
k'mo b'Tisha B'Av, it's not mentioned.
ובימי זקנותו חזר והתיר. u'vimei ziknuto chazar v'hitir. But then when he
got older,
anyway he reversed himself and he said you are allowed to learn
those areas.
And you know by the way going just directly sort of a
little touching on your point Charlie, ובירושלמי אמרו אבל שונה במקום שאינו
רגיל, u'v'Yerushalmi amru avel shoneh b'makom she'eino ragil, you can even learn
in a place that you don't normally learn from, so it's not
as pleasurable because it's a topic you normally don't learn and it's
more foreign to you. Okay, so anyway he goes through this issue
about whether we have the types of allowances we have by תשעה
באב. Tisha B'Av. Now another interesting thing in terms of the incompleteness
of the list is a point, a conceptual point I was making
to you before. If you look at the earlier תוספות אלו דברים
שהאבל אסור בהן, Tosafot eilu devarim she'ha'avel assur bahen, he
says הכא לא קחשיב דברים שמצווה עליו, hacha lo kachashiv devarim she'mitzvah
alav, כגון כפיית המיטה ועטיפת הראש. k'gon kfiyat hamita v'atifat harosh. We're
not talking about practices, active practices like turning up the bed and
the veiling of the head, right? Remember we also mentioned that. ולא
קחשיב אלא מילי דאסור בהן, v'lo kachashiv ela milei d'assur bahen, only
things that are forbidden, things like the
prohibitions. תפילין ושאילת שלום לא קחשיב דאיכא דאמרי הכי ואיכא דאמרי הכי,
Tfillin u'she'eilat shalom lo kachashiv d'ika d'amri hachi v'ika d'amri hachi, and
even there it's not complete because it doesn't mention תפילין, tfillin, it
doesn't mention asking after the welfare because תפילין tfillin is only day
one, שאילת שלום she'eilat shalom לפי lefi is a difference between the
first three days and the last four days. So anyway it's an
incomplete list. But one of the things that תוספות Tosafot says conceptually
is a reason to leave things off the list is distinguishing between
practices of אבלות avelut and prohibitions of אבלות. avelut. Okay. Now again
as I said, conceptually it's not always clear which is which. You
could say an אבל avel is forbidden to wear shoes, or you
could say a practice of אבלות avelut is going barefoot. Right? An
אבל avel is forbidden to sit on a chair or practice of
אבלות avelut is sitting on a low chair, you can conceptualize it
either way. And it's interesting because you'll remember the גמרא Gemara by
the way that speaks about right before the רגל, regel, if a
person was מקיים כפיית המיטה, mekayem kfiyat hamita, the רגל regel was
מבטלה. mevatlah. And you know what we do nowadays? If like there's
a burial right before let's say a רגל? regel?
Sit for like an hour?
Well yeah, but we also just say like make sure a person
takes off his shoes. So then you'll actually have done a practice
of אבלות avelut before the רגל. regel. So is taking off of
shoes a practice of אבלות avelut or is it just a prohibition
of אבלות? avelut? So conceptually it's very interesting to think about the
way things can be categorized.
But anyway we did three days before a רגל? regel?
No, we just do, yeah we פוסקין poskin the position of one
day, of even an hour. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, second wide line. אבל ג' ימים הראשונים
אסור להניח תפילין. avel gimmel yamim harishonim assur lehaniach tfillin. The first
three days, now we know we פוסקין poskin only one day, but
this is reflecting the idea that the first three days in the
משנה, Mishnah, the idea in the משנה Mishnah that three days are
the key אבלות, avelut, so therefore three days אסור assur in תפילין,
tfillin, which is pretty radical, not doing a מצווה. mitzvah. Three days
אסור assur in תפילין. tfillin. ומשלישי ואילך ושלישי בכלל, u'mishlishi v'eilach v'shlishi
bichlal, now starting on day three on, including day three, מותר להניח
תפילין. mutar lehaniach tfillin. Can put on תפילין. tfillin. So it's a
very bizarre way of saying it. Can't wear תפילין tfillin for three
days, but starting on day three he can wear תפילין, tfillin, so
you're really only saying can't wear תפילין tfillin for two days. Presumably
it's conceptually an idea of מקצת היום ככולו *miktzat hayom kekulo*. Conceptually
it's three days, but if you begin the first minute of day
three without wearing תפילין Tefillin, *tefillin*, then for the rest of day
three you can wear תפילין Tefillin, *tefillin*. Okay. ואם באו פנים חדשות
*v'im ba'u panim chadashot*, but if new people have are now coming
and paying a
שבעה shiva? *shivah* call, אינו חולץ *eino choletz*, you don't have to
take off your תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. Meaning דברי רבי אליעזר *divrei Rabbi
Eliezer*. That's what רבי *Rabbi* אליעזר *Eliezer* says. Meaning somebody would think,
oh look, you're wearing תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* now, presumably you the you
this guy was wearing תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin* even at the beginning of
אבלות *aveilut*. You don't have to worry about what people are thinking.
You already practiced two days of of not wearing תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*,
you can keep them on from there on in. רבי יהושע אומר
*Rabbi Yehoshua omer*, רבי *Rabbi* יהושע *Yehoshua* says, by the way, what's
clear here also the idea that when they would wear תפילין Tefillin
*tefillin*, they'd wear the whole day because your this guy sitting שבעה
shiva *shivah* wearing his תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin*. רבי יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua
omer*, אמר בשני ימים הראשונים אסור להניח *amar b'shnei yamim harishonim assur
lehaniach*, it's not three days, it's only the first two days. And
משני והשני בכלל *mishani v'hasheni bikhlal*, but starting on day two, including
day two, מותר להניח תפילין *mutar lehaniach tefillin*, which really means only
one day a person can't wear תפילין *tefillin*, which is how we
פוסקין *pasken*. Although again conceptually there's an idea of a second day.
ואם באו פנים חדשות *v'im ba'u panim chadashot*, so in that way
he's more lenient, only day one. Then the following way he's more
strict. That if people new people show up after day one and
the אבל avel *aveil* is wearing תפילין *tefillin*, חולץ *choletz*, he would
have to take them off as a way of demonstrating that, you
know, he hasn't been wearing תפילין *tefillin* the whole time.
אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Hisda*, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר *mai ta'ama
de-Rabbi Eliezer*? What's the reason of רבי *Rabbi* אליעזר *Eliezer*'s that says
two days of not wearing תפילין *tefillin*? That now makes two days
the עיקר אבלות *ikar aveilut*. Even if conceptually it's three like the
משנה *mishnah*, but it boils down to two. דכתיב *De-khitiv*, because the
verse says, ויטמו ימי בכי אבל avel's משה *v'yitmu yimei bekhi eivel
Moshe*, the days of the crying over משה *Moshe*, plural. So there's
a minimum of two days because the minimum of plural is two.
Okay, so אמר רב עינא *amar Rav Eina*, מאי טעמא דרבי יהושע
*mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehoshua*? What's the reason of רבי *Rabbi* יהושע *Yehoshua*'s
that says the one day is the עיקר אבלות *ikar aveilut*, at
least for this issue of תפילין *tefillin*? דכתיב *De-khitiv*, ואחריתה כיום מר
*v'acharitah k'yom mar*, and the afterwards aftermath of death is like a
bitter day in the singular. Okay, so again the assumption here is
is that when it comes to overriding a biblical מצוה *mitzvah* of
not wearing תפילין *tefillin*, we're not going to have that for the
entire period of אבלות *aveilut*, only for what we consider to be
the עיקר *ikar*, the essence of it. And here the debate, you
can frame it as three versus two, that's what it sounded like
conceptually, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* boils it down to two versus
one. Okay, so on the one hand that's the three idea as
we saw in our משנה *mishnah*. The one idea is the way
we פוסקין *pasken*. We פוסקין *pasken* only don't wear תפילין *tefillin* the
first day, that if a person only observes day one of אבלות
*aveilut*, the regular overrides, that ultimately it boils down to day one.
And as I've mentioned to you before in the ראשונים *Rishonim*, the
discussion of is there a דאורייתא *de-oraita* aspect of אבלות *aveilut* is
that most state it regarding day one. Afterwards it's considered to be
completely דרבנן *de-rabbanan*. I mean obviously practices go back to biblical times,
but in sense of the sense of a formal legal obligation, the
question is that might it be biblical is limited to the issue
of day one. Yes, Charlie?
When they're starting counting day one, day two here, are they starting
with the death or the burial?
Burial, burial. We're not talking about אנינות aninut *aninut*, talking about אבלות
*aveilut*. Okay, we'll get to that aspect in a little bit. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. So on the day
of the burial you don't put on
תפילין *tefillin*? Yeah, yeah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. רבי יהושע נמי הכתיב ויטמו ימי *Rabbi Yehoshua nami hakhitiv v'yitmu
yimei*? What do you do with the verse that says plural by
משה *Moshe* to count like a minimum of two days? אמר לך
*Amar lakh*, שאני משה דתקיף אבליה *shani Moshe detakif aveileh*. משה *Moshe*
was different, the אבלות *aveilut* was very intense. ורבי אליעזר נמי הכתיב
ואחריתה כיום מר *V'Rabbi Eliezer nami hakhitiv v'acharitah k'yom mar*, the aftermath
is like a bitter day in the singular? עיקר מרירותא חד יומא
הוא *Ikar meriruta chad yoma hu*. Okay, I can concede that the
real bitterness is one day, but the real אבלות *aveilut* is at
least two days. All right. אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*, הלכה halacha כרבי
אליעזר בחליצה *halakhah ke-Rabbi Eliezer b'chalitzah*, והלכה כרבי יהושע בהנחה *v'halakhah ke-Rabbi
Yehoshua b'hanachah*. We're ruling leniently in both ways, which should not be
a surprise to you. We rule like רבי *Rabbi* אליעזר *Eliezer* בחליצה
*b'chalitzah* that a person does not have to remove the תפילין *tefillin*
if they, you know, on the later days. And we rule like
רבי *Rabbi* יהושע *Yehoshua* that after day one a person's allowed to
put on תפילין *tefillin*. Okay, so the most lenient: put on תפילין
*tefillin* after day one and from that point on don't take it
off. Now, there's a little ambiguity here because the position don't take
it off was said in the context of from day three on
don't take it off. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says איבעיא להו
*ibaia lehu*, they raised the question: בשני לעולא חולץ או אינו חולץ
*B'sheni l'Ulla choletz o eino choletz*? When you say we rule don't
take it off, that was derived on a position that says don't
take it off starting on day three. So what would you say
about day two? תא שמע *Ta shema*, come and hear, אמר עולא
*amar Ulla*, חולץ ומניח choletz umniach, אפילו מאה פעמים *choletz u-maniach afilu
meiah pe'amim*, that no, that there will be a context where you
would have to where a person would have to take it off
and put it back on even a hundred times. So what would
be that context? Not day one, day one a person doesn't put
it on. Not day three because עולא *Ulla* ruled day three you
don't take it off. So it must be on day two is
where he sort of splits, you know, is in this gray zone
where a person puts it on but would have to take it
off if new people would show up. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami
hakhi*, it was also taught like this: ומתאמרי ליה יהודה בן תימא
אומר *v'mitamri leh Yehuda ben Teima omer*, חולץ ומניח אפילו מאה פעמים
*choletz u-maniach afilu meiah pe'amim*. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא Rava
*Rava* says, כיון שהניח שוב אינו חולץ *kivan she-heniach shuv eino choletz*.
Again, not to surprise you. That we'll at the end we come
back to the most lenient of all the possible possibilities. Once a
person is putting it on on day two, would not have to
take it off even if new person showed up. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, דהא רבא הוא דאמר הלכה כתנא דידן דאמר
שלשה. deha Rava hu d'amar halacha ketanna didan d'amar shlosha. This whole
issue of תפילין, one day or three days, right? How could רבא
Rava wind up with the most lenient opinion? רבא Rava's says earlier
that a person has to observe three days of אבילות aveilus before
the רגל regel can annul it. So רבא is not saying the
most lenient. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מצוה שאני. mitzvah shanei.
It's one thing to say three days is a minimum before the
רגל regel could be מבטל, mevatel, there is a conceptual idea of
a three-day minimum. But the power to override תפילין, that we're going
to limit just to one day. Okay, so that's at least רבא's
position. We say all of them is only one day. Overriding תפילין
is one day, minimum to observe in before רגל regel annuls it
is one day. We take the most lenient position of all of
this. We don't do חולץ ומניח, we take the most lenient position.
Yes.
So the הלכה is assuming you're buried on day one, you wouldn't
put תפילין on day one because you're an אונן. onen. On day
two also you're not putting them on? No.
If the burial ends the אנינות and begins the אבילות. aveilus. So
it's that day, a person is buried, even if the burial takes
place at seven in the morning on day, you know, so for
the rest of the day, the אבלים aveilim don't put on תפילין.
If the person is buried at 4:00 PM, the אבלים aveilim haven't
been putting on תפילין until that time because they're אוננים, onanim, but
now from 4:00 PM until it gets dark, they're still not putting
on תפילין because it's day one of אבילות. aveilus. So
the one day that we're
talking about is
the day of burial, right, exactly, until nightfall, right. Okay, תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. So that was about תורה Tora and תפילין. Now we
turn back to issues of doing work. אבל ג' ימים ראשונים אסור
במלאכה. Avel gimel yamim rishonim assur b'melacha. An אבל avel the first
three days does not do work. ואפילו עני המתפרנס מן הצדקה. V'afilu
ani hamitparneis min hatzdakah. Even if it is a poor person who
needs to be supported by communal funds and nevertheless, you know, he
doesn't have anything to eat, he should be able to produce some
work to put some food on the table and not to have
to take as much charity. No, does not do it. But that's
only for the first three days. מכאן
ואילך עושה בצינעה בתוך ביתו. Mikan v'eilach oseh betzina betoch beito. After
those that period, however, a person can do in private in his
house. ואשה טווה בפלך בתוך ביתה. V'ishah tova b'pelekh betoch beita. And
a woman could like sew with the spindle in her house, like
you know, again, I don't know exactly what the context is. First
of all, presumably it means after the first three days, but is
that because like you know, sometimes women like to do knitting, so
it's not really considered מלאכה? melacha? But then it would be funny.
Or does it mean that no, that somehow that's like her again,
domestic assumption of like domestic duties? Like somebody, you know, a button
comes off of their shirt, so it would be the woman who
would sew it back on or something. Not exactly clear to me
what the full context of that is. But again, that is seen
as something that is not fully at the status of מלאכה melacha
or private enough that it's allowed. Now the big ambiguity of this
גמרא Gemara is after three days a person can do in private,
what context are we talking about? Right? We said don't do for
the first three days don't do מלאכה melacha even an עני המתפרנס
מן הצדקה. ani hamitparneis min hatzdakah. And after the three days it
can be done in private in the house. Does that mean anybody
can do in private in the house after the first three days?
Or are we going back on the case of the עני? ani?
Right? So are we saying that for the עני, ani, even an
עני ani has to observe the first three days and afterwards can
do it privately? Or are we saying no, for everybody, the איסור
מלאכה issur melacha is only three days? Okay, it sounds a little
bit more like the latter, right, because it starts by saying אבל
ג' ימים ראשונים אסור. avel gimel yamim rishonim assur. It sounds like
the general rule for everybody is only the first three days. Anyway,
תוספות Tosafot has a major discussion about that that goes back and
forth between those
positions. Okay. And does not really come to a clear conclusion.
Can you have others do work
for you all the time? That is again not so clear in
the גמרא Gemara when it spoke about other people doing work, that
was when the אבילות aveilus was broken up and part of it
was observed afterwards. It wasn't a standard case. It wasn't so clear.
Let's take a look.
If you can't do work, which implies somebody else can.
I understand. But others, whatever, it's not so clear. Let's keep on
reading, see what we say. Okay. But anyway, that had to, so
but that was the issue of work, again, there is a lot
of these ambiguities. We had a discussion before about other people, but
that also sounded like that was a special case. David asked the
other time about the issue about what does it mean, other people
can't do work for you. Does it mean if you own a
business, you can't, you know, you have to sell your business during
that time? Presumably it means also giving over the work that's your
personal responsibility. But anyway, a lot of unclear parameters about the issue
of מלאכה. melacha. Now we turn out to something else. Somebody, I'm
waiting for somebody to ask me, where does it say that an
אבל's avel not allowed to leave his house during the whole period
of שבעה? shiva Well, the answer is it doesn't exactly. But there
are things that sort of suggest the idea of being there to
receive the מנחמים menachamim and the מנחמים menachamim come to the person.
Okay, and there's clearly this issue about like things like not doing
work or not involving oneself in other activities that distract one from
their responsibilities. We're going to see another whole issue about the שאלת
שלום. she'ilas shalom. So there are, we'll see sort of different things
that point in that direction. But you don't see like a black
and white statement that says don't leave the house, and we know
that an אבל avel has to leave the house, an אבל avel,
can leave the house, right? So it is interesting though that כאן,
kan, the way that that sort of in our minds, I think
for a lot of people actually, I was once thinking about doing
a little, a little test, whatever, a little question, ask people what
does שבעה shiva mean? How many people know שבעה shiva, means seven,
and some people might associate שבעה shiva, with sitting, right? Sitting שבעה,
shiva, לשבת, lasheves, although that's not even grammatically correct, right? But anyway,
but what would it be? Would it be שביה, shevi'ah, right? The
sitting, שבעה, shiva שבות, shevus, no
ישיבה yeshiva is sitting, right? Yeah, שבו, shevu, anyway, what would be
the abstract
noun? Would it be, anyway, whatever. Anyway, but the concept we have
is that the primary point is staying in the house, where that
is not explicitly said here. Let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. tano rabbanan. אבל ג' ימים הראשונים אינו הולך לבית
האבל. avel gimel yamim harishonim eino holech leveit ha'avel. First three days
will not go to another mourner's house. Now again, does that mean
a person can't leave his or her own house? No, going to
another mourner's house is that whole sort of social interaction, and also
positions somebody as a consoler rather than a mourner, and a time
when a person is in, him or herself is in mourning. So
it doesn't mean you don't, a person doesn't leave the house, but
you don't go to another אבל's avel house. ומכאן ואילך, mikan ve'eilach,
and again notice the emphasis on the first three days again giving
those special status. ומכאן ואילך הולך ואינו יושב במקום המנחמים אלא במקום
המתנחמים. mikan ve'eilach holech ve'eino yoshev bimkom hamenachamim ela bimkom hamitnachamim. From
that point on, the remainder of the שבעה, shiva the days four
through seven, a person can go to another mourner's house but doesn't
sit in the place where the consoler sits, but sits in the
place where the consoled sit. You've, so sits together with the other
mourners. Again, because even if a person can be involved, you know,
to pay a שבעה shiva call, a person still themselves can't take
themselves out of their own sort of identity as also a mourner.
תנו רבנן. tano rabbanan. We taught. אבל ג' ימים הראשונים אסור בשאילת
שלום. avel gimel yamim harishonim asur beshe'eilas shalom. First three days cannot
involve, cannot do a asking after people's well-being like greeting, but as
we'll see, it's more than just a hello. Okay, משלושה ועד שבע
משיב ואינו שואל. mishlosha ve'ad shiva meshiv ve'eino shoel. From three to
seven, it's a person can respond if somebody asks after their well-being
but cannot initiate. מכאן ואילך שואל ומשיב כדרכו. mikan ve'eilach shoel umeshiv
kedarko. Afterwards a person can both respond and initiate. So by the
way, notice the parallel, notice the parallel of all these things, where
they're aspects of social interaction, whether it is doing מלאכה, melacha, right?
מלאכה melacha is a question, is that about distracting oneself, is that
about the social aspects of the מלאכה? melacha? But there's doing the
מלאכה, melacha, there's going to another mourner's house and there's שאילת שלום,
she'eilas shalom, and all of them there's a difference between the first
three days and afterwards. Okay, let's take a look now at what
the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says, שלושה ימים הראשונים
אסור בשאילת שלום, shelosha yamim harishonim asur beshe'eilas shalom, the first three
days are not allowed to שאילת שלום, she'eilas shalom, והתניא vehatanya we
have in a ברייתא. Braitah. מעשה שמתו בניו של רבי עקיבא. ma'aseh
shemetu banav shel Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva's sons died. Note the plural,
I mean, these are tragic just hearing this about the death of
children. Before we had a grandchild died, right? Okay,
נכנסו כל ישראל, nichnesu kol Yisrael, the entire Jewish people came, obviously
a large number of people came, והספידום הספד גדול vehispidum hesped gadol
and they gave them a great eulogy. בשעת פטירתן besha'as petirasan when
everybody was getting up to leave, עמד רבי עקיבא על הספסל גדול,
amad Rabbi Akiva al hasafsal gadol, Rabbi Akiva got up on a
big like a stool so he guess he could be heard, ואמר
ve'amar and he said the following, אחינו בית ישראל, acheinu beit Yisrael,
our brothers house of Israel. שמעו shemu listen, אפילו שני בנים חתנים
מנוחם הוא בשביל כבוד שעשיתם. afilu shenei banim chatanim menucham hu bishvil
kavod she'asitem. Even if
it was two sons who were bridegrooms, which presumably means it was
more tragic because they had been married or maybe it means that
they had been adults as opposed to if they were infants, right?
Even on their wedding day, I would have been consoled בשביל כבוד
שעשיתם, bishvil kavod she'asitem, because of the great honor that you did.
ואם בשביל עקיבא באתם, ve'im bishvil Akiva basem, if you just came
for like me, like I'm
an עקיבא, Akiva, like I'm a guy, I'm your friend, הרי כמה
עקיבא בשוק, harei kamma Akiva bashuk, there are lots of עקיבאs Akiva
in the marketplace. It wasn't for my sake you came. אלא כך
אמרתם, ela kach amartem, but thus you said the following. תורת אלוהיו
בלבו, Torat Elokav belibo, you came because of your respect for תורה,
Torah, because I'm a תורה Torah scholar. So he's not doing this
to give himself a pat on the back, he's doing it to
acknowledge that it wasn't just because of their, that they knew him,
that they were friends with him, it was out of respect for
תורה. Torah. וכל שכן ששכרכם כפול, vekol sheken she'secharchem kaful, how much
more therefore is your reward doubled because in your act of paying
a שבעה shiva call, you also showed respect for תורה. Torah. לכו
לבתיכם לשלום, lechu levateichem leshalom, go to your homes in peace. So
how do you see he did something wrong? Because he said לכו
לשלום. lechu leshalom. So that's שאילת שלום, she'eilas shalom, wishing somebody peace.
Now by the way again it's interesting is what exactly does שאילת
שלום she'eilas shalom mean? I mean we translated this as saying hello,
but you know I think שאילת שלום she'eilas shalom can mean two
possible things, one could be the... general asking after somebody's welfare, which
is again too much of like not welfare as you would say
to an אבל, avel, like you know how you doing, I feel
bad or whatever, you know, but sort of more the normal types
of discourse of hey how's everything going, which is obviously you know
not appropriate in terms of the social interaction, so from this story
you see that the emphasis might be on the word שלום, shalom,
right, like שלום עליכם Shalom Aleichem or לכו לשלום, Lechu l'shalom, because
it's like it's not appropriate to say peace, like peace is also
שלמות, shlemut, right, at this time, this is not a time to
be wishing somebody for for שלמות, shlemut, so it could be very
much the emphasis on the word שלום. shalom. So anyway you see
that it was during, it was right there, presumably it was during
the first three days, it sounds like it was right after their
deaths, and there was שאלת שלום, she'elat shalom, so the גמרא Gemara
says כבוד רבים שאני, kevod rabbim shani, that's different, he did it
for the honoring the masses, they honored his Torah, he honored the
masses that came there, it was appropriate. Okay, so first three days
no שאלת שלום. she'elat shalom. Now we get to the next stage.
מג' ועד ז' משיב ואינו שואל, Migimmel v'ad zayin meshiv v'eino shoel,
from day three, not exactly clear day three or day four, to
day seven, you can the אבל avel. respond but cannot initiate. מכאן
ואילך שואל ומשיב כדרכו, Mikan v'eilach shoel u'meshiv k'darko, afterwards he can
even initiate. ורמינהי, u'reminhi, I'll ask you on this, we have another
teaching, notice by the way the various teachings here on the side
reference מסכת שמחות, Masechet Semachot, which is a collection of Tannaitic material,
I mean was edited later in the אמורא Amora period or maybe
the final editing in the גאון Gaon period, but there's Tannaitic material
collected around issues of אבילות. aveilut. Okay, so here's what we see
there. המוצא
את חבירו אבל בתוך שלשים יום, Hamotzei et chaveiro avel betoch shloshim
yom, if somebody finds a you know bumps into his friend and
is still within the thirty days of אבילות, aveilut, so after the
שבעה shiva but in the middle of the thirty, מדבר עמו תנחומין,
midaber imo tanchumin, it's still appropriate to speak words of consolation, ואינו
שואל בשלומו, v'eino shoel b'shlomo, not appropriate to to ask after their
שלום, shalom, their well-being. Okay, so it's still a period of consolation
during שלשים. shloshim. לאחר שלשים יום, Le'achar shloshim yom, after שלשים, shloshim,
שואל בשלומו ואינו מדבר עמו תנחומין, shoel b'shlomo v'eino midaber imo tanchumin,
it's the reverse, you ask after their well-being, the person is now
back into society, back into the normal stream of things, and you
not only do you not have to, you're not supposed to speak
words of תנחומין, tanchumin, because as we'll see like the person's wound
is starting to heal now and maybe you know you are going
to like reopen it, so that it actually would be inappropriate to
directly address the aspects of תנחומין. tanchumin. We'll see about that more
in a what,
if I didn't when my father died and I didn't see somebody
after 45 days, I really appreciated hearing
I'm so sorry to hear, right, yeah
and if I didn't, I felt like
yeah why aren't you saying something, that's very interesting, so the question
also is what's the aspect of תנחומין, tanchumin, is it one statement
like oh I'm so sorry to hear about what happened or is
it like you know was it like like oh you must have
felt so terrible, how hard was that for you, whatever, which is
you know that would be like a little bit like inappropriate at
that time, right,
I mean inappropriate at any time, well
all right whatever anyway it's interesting we will see a line coming
up that says מדבר עמו מן הצד, midaber imo min hatzad, which
maybe is trying to strike this balance that there's some type of
an acknowledgment but it's not like a שבעה shiva call that's being
made you know it's not a more intensive but I really appreciate
that point you know so it's exactly striking that balance. Okay, מתה
אשתו, meta ishto,
now for a person's wife to a person a man's wife died
ונשא אשה אחרת, v'nasa isha acheret, and he married another woman and
this in the context is within thirty days, and normally you're not
supposed to get married within thirty the first thirty days, but we'll
see exceptions coming up later if a person has children and his
you know man has children small children and his wife died special
allowances are given with the assumption that men are not able to
raise their kids and take care of their kids so allowances that
they can even get married during שלשים. shloshim. Okay, so if that
happens here אינו רשאי ליכנס לביתו לדבר עמו תנחומין, eino rashai likaneis
l'veito l'daber imo tanchumin, for you cannot go into the person's house
to pay you know to have talk about like a type of
a well after שבעה shiva but anyway a שבעה shiva call תנחומין
tanchumin call because the wife is around the new wife is around.
מצאו בשוק, metza'o bashuk, now if you found the guy in the
marketplace apparently this person who got remarried after within the thirty days
of his wife's dying אומר לו בשפה רפה ובכובד ראש, omer lo
b'safa rafa u'v'koved rosh, you speak words of תנחומין tanchumin but in
a literally in a light sort of you know words and with
a heaviness of the head, so it's not exactly clear what that
means you know but it means in a respectful way you know
it's very complicated right now his wife died and you want to
speak give him you know say some words of תנחומין tanchumin but
he's remarried to this other woman you don't want to undermine her
status and what's going on with her so obviously you have to
be very delicate but whatever you're doing don't do it in the
house. Okay, anyway what do you see from all this, you see
that even during שלשים shloshim you're not supposed to be שואל בשלומו
shoel b'shlomo and we said that after
after שבעה shiva, you're allowed to be do שאלת שלום she'elat shalom
so what's the story during the שלשים shloshim period? So אמר אבידי
בר אבין amar Avidi bar Avin הוא שואל בשלום חבירים שהם שרויים
בשלום hu shoel b'shalom chaveirim shehem shruyim b'shalom notice again here the
emphasis on the text on the actual word שלום shalom during the...
If during the שלשים shloshim period, he can ask after other people's
well-being, because they're in a state of שלמות shleimut and of peace,
so he can say שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, מה שלומך, ma shlomcha,
you know, and so on. That he can do because he's asking
after their state of שלום, shalom, so the only aspect, therefore, is
the social intercourse, and that's appropriate after שבעה shiva, during שלשים. shloshim.
So the social aspect is okay, the שלום shalom aspect, as long
as it's after their שלום, shalom, that's appropriate.
But where are we? אחרים אין שואלין בשלומו. Acherim ein sho'alin b'shlomo.
Other people can have social intercourse with him, but they can't ask
after his שלום shalom during the period of שלשים, shloshim, שהוא אינו
שרוי בשלום, shehu eino sharui b'shalom, he still is not in a
state of שלמות. shleimut. So that's how we resolve it: after שבעה,
shiva, there can be social intercourse, there can be שואל בשלומו sho'el
b'shlomo about the non-אבל'ס avel's שלום, shalom, but during the שלשים, shloshim,
a person cannot ask after the אבל'ס avel's שלום. shalom. Now, the
problem is that that doesn't fit the text. והא מדקתני משיב, Ve-ha
midekatni meshiv, מכלל דשאלינן ליה. michlal desha'alinan leh.
One minute, the text said that after שבעה, shiva, it says that
he can ask and respond to שאלת שלום. she'ilat shalom. So how
can he- if he's responding to שאלת שלום she'ilat shalom after שבעה,
shiva, it means people are asking after his שלום? shalom? So the
גמרא Gemara says: no, דלא ידעי. delo yad'ei. People asked him without
being aware that they weren't- that he was an אבל, avel, or
without being aware they weren't supposed to ask. So what do you
do? Somebody says- you know, somebody says this, how are you supposed
to respond? So then it's allowed to respond. So the says: one
minute, אי הכי התם נמי. ee hachi hatam nami. So if it's
that person was unaware and asked, then
respond even during the first three days, or you know... So the
says: no, התם מודע להו ולא מהדר להו. hatam moda lehu velo
mehadar lehu. During the first three days, even if a person said
מה שלומך, ma shlomcha, you know, שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, you say:
"I can't respond, I'm an אבל." avel, So you actually, you know,
you have to- you can't respond even in that context. הכא, Hacha,
after the first three days, when a person can be משיב, meshiv,
לא צריך להודיעינהו. lo tzarich lehod'inhu. You don't have to say to
the guy, "Hey, maybe you didn't realize I'm an אבל," avel you
just say, "Yeah, שלום עליכם," shalom aleichem, you respond. So it's interesting
again, walking that line between what's appropriate for the person's state of
אבילות aveilus and not making the other person feel awkward, and that's
the difference. So now what has the גמרא said? The גמרא said
during the first three, even if a person says to the אבל,
avel "שלום עליכם," shalom aleichem, the אבל avel doesn't respond. From three
to seven, the אבל- avel, you're not supposed to ask the אבל
avel the entire שלשים, shloshim, but if a person did ask the
אבל, avel from three to seven, the אבל avel is allowed to
respond, but he does not ask. And after seven, the אבל'ס avel's
allowed to ask, because he's asking- that's only the social intercourse aspect
of it, he's asking somebody else's שלום, shalom, it's not about his
שלום, shalom, he's allowed to ask. So for the entire שלשים, shloshim,
you're not supposed to ask. If you- unaware- ask, the אבל avel
can respond anytime after the first three days. The entire שבעה, shiva,
the אבל avel. doesn't ask somebody else because of the social intercourse
aspect, but after the שבעה, shiva the אבל avel does. I just
want to read before we end one more line, which gets back
to the issue we were discussing. Let's just do one more line.
The גמרא says: ורמינהו, U'remi'enhu, I'll ask you on this. המוצא את
חבירו אבל בתוך י"ב חודש, Hamotze et chaveiro avel betoch yod-bet chodesh,
up to the whole year, מדבר עמו תנחומין. medaber imo tanchumin.
You speak תנחומין, tanchumin, even the whole year you can do words
of תנחומין, tanchumin, ואינו שואל בשלומו, ve'eino sho'el b'shlomo, and you don't
ask after the שלום. shalom. לאחר י"ב חודש שואל בשלומו ואינו מדבר
עמו תנחומין. Le'achar yod-bet chodesh sho'el b'shlomo ve'eino medaber imo tanchumin.
After the twelve months, so you- you ask after the well-being and
you don't mention תנחומין, tanchumin, but here going back to the point
right before, אבל מדבר עמו מן הצד. avel medaber imo min hatzad.
Even after the year, you make some allusion to it. So it's
again walking this tightrope, like acknowledging it, but not getting into it.
So I mean, I think that that's, you know, very appropriate to
the point you were asking, how much is מדבר עמו תנחומין. medaber
imo tanchumin. So אמר רבי מאיר, amar Rabbi Meir, and here comes
the issue about asking תנחומין- tanchumin about the more focused תנחומין tanhumin,
sort of, you know, discussion when it's actually a while since the
death. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, I just wanted to read
this one משל mashal before we end it today. המוצא את חבירו
אבל אחר י"ב חודש ומדבר עמו תנחומין, Hamotze et chaveiro avel achar
yod-bet chodesh umedaber imo tanchumin, if it's after a year already and
the person is talking about, you know, sort of speaking words of
תנחומין tanhumin? in the normal way that one would speak even, you
know, during the שבעה, shiva so למה הוא דומה, le-ma hu domeh,
what is he similar to? לאדם שנשברה רגלו, le-adam shenishbera raglo, a
person whose leg broke, וחיתה, ve-chayeta, and it got and it healed,
מצאו רופא, matza'o rofe, and a doctor came along and found him,
ואמר לו, ve-amar lo, and he said to him: בוא אצלי, bo
etzli, you know, come to me, שאני שוברה וארפאנה, she-ani shovera ve'erpa'ena,
I'll break it and I'll reset it, כדי שתדע שסממנין שלי יפין,
kedei she-teda she-sammanin sheli yaffin, so you'll know how good my medicine
is. Wow. And by the way, this sounds like- absurd, but you
know, this actually happens a lot, sadly, when people are paying שבעה
shiva calls and whatever, they're very focused on what- what's going on
for them, not what's going on for the אבל. avel Right, you
know, and the idea is, like, you know, it doesn't matter whether
you feel bad that you didn't get a chance to pay a
שבעה shiva call, and you want to do your שבעה shiva. now
a year later. You should be thinking about what's going on for
this person and what's appropriate and what this person needs at this
time. Okay, anyway so that's a very powerful imagery and just to
answer the question here, it seems like it's a year, before we
said it's only שלשים יום, sheloshim yom, so the answer probably should
be obvious and that's the last line the גמרא says לא קשיא
הא באביו ואמו הא בשאר קרובים. lo kashya ha b'av v'eima ha
b'sh'ar krovim. So it's what's different about father and mother, that this
status lasts a year, other קרובים krovim it only is for a
month, the idea of asking after the שלשים. sheloshim. What, התם נמי
ידבר עמהם תנחומין מן הצד? hatam nami yedaber imahem tanhumin min hatzad?
So the גמרא says okay, so in the case when we said
after thirty days don't speak תנחומין, tanhumin why don't we mention this
idea of מן הצד, min hatzad, this allusion? It says אין הכי
נמי, in hachi nami, you're right, it is, it's true, ומאי אינו
מדבר עמהם תנחומין, u'mai eino medaber imahem tanhumin, what do we mean
you don't speak תנחומין? כדרכו, kedarko, in the normal way, אבל מדבר
עמו מן הצד, aval medaber imo min hatzad, exactly going back to
the point before that even after the month you don't do a
normal תנחומין but there is some reference to it, some allusion to
it, some mention of it. Okay, so bottom line is a person
does not ask after the שלום shalom of another for thirty days,
for אביו ואמו av v'eima it's supposed to be a year. Again,
that doesn't mean just greeting, it has a particular weight to שאלת
שלום. she'elat shalom. Does not ask, if asked, the אבל avel will
respond any time after three days. First three days the אבל does
not respond. The אבל himself doesn't ask after other people's well-being already
after the שבעה because then it's only the social intercourse. He's asking
after other people's well-being and that can already be after the שבעה.